Guide to the Theresa El-Amin Papers, 1960s-2012 RL.00357
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Printed Materials, 1978-2010 and undated, 3 boxes
  The Printed Materials series includes newsletters, magazines, journals, fliers, handouts, and other miscellaneous materials from a wide variety of sources. The first box contains runs of various periodicals, including Forward Motion, In Defense of Marxism, and Labor Notes. These runs are incomplete and represent only a sampling of the publication. The second box of printed materials relates largely to El-Amin's union involvement, and features miscellaneous union publications from the 1980s-2000s. There is a small amount of earlier material, mainly in the Historical Pamphlets folder, which includes publications on desegregation and its impact on unions. The remainder of the series is also largely miscellaneous, with one or two issues of a wide range of newsletters, magazines, or organizational reports. Where possible, these publications and printed materials have been sorted by subject.
  Additional publications are included in the Organizations and Movements series, where they have been filed with the organization that created them. These include Solidarity Bulletins, Black Workers for Justice Justice Speaks, Coalition of Labor Women newsletters, and a wide range of union publications from the Service Employees International Union.
  - Against the Current issues, 1998-2010, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Committees of Correspondence Corresponder issues, 1997-1999 (Box 13)
  - Forward Motion issues, 1987-1989, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - In Defense of Marxism issues, 1988-1997, 7 folders (Box 13)
  - Labor Notes issues, 1991-2009, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Liberation and Marxism issues, 1989-1994 (Box 13)
  - Orange County Rape Crisis Center newsletters, 2007-2008 (Box 13)
  - Political Affairs issues, 1988-1997 (Box 13)
  - Third Force issues, 1993-1997, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - The Nation issues, 1996-2001 (Box 13)
  - Vibration issues, 1987-1993 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous solidarity newsletters, 1989-1993 (Box 14)
  - Ohio AFL-CIO magazines, 1996-1997 (Box 14)
  - Dollars and Sense issues, 1992-1997 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous union materials, 1950s-2000s
    - Magazines from various unions, 1980s-1990s, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Newsletters and reports, 1990s-2001 (Box 14)
    - Printed materials, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Historical pamphlets, 1955-1980s (Box 14)
    - Pamphlets, 1970s-1990s (Box 14)
    - History articles, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Reports (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets, 1990s-2000s, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous newsletters, 5 folders
    - General subjects, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Africa (Box 14)
    - Education/children (Box 14)
    - Environment (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous newsletters, 5 folders (Box 15)
    - Faith/religion (Box 15)
    - Labor/unions (Box 15)
    - Politics/political parties (Box 15)
    - Poverty/class (Box 15)
    - Race/racism (Box 15)
  - Clippings (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous fliers, handouts, and organizational materials, 1990s-2000s, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous articles and reports, 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous journals (Box 15)
  - Hal Draper: Karl Marx's Theory of Revolution, undated (Box 15)
  - Mindy Thompson: National Negro Labor Council: A History, 1978 (Box 15)
  - Dissent, 1965 and 1966, 2 issues (Box 22)
  - The Negro Protest, in the Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, January 1965 (Box 22)
  - The Crisis, December 1960 (Box 22)
  - What is Revolutionary Leadership?, Labour Review articles, 1964 (Box 22)
  - Freedomways, W.E.B. DuBois memorial issue, 1965 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials about Islam, 1995-1997 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials, 2010 (Box 22)
- Personal Files and Correspondence, 1982-2009 and undated, 1 box
  Includes some of El-Amin's personal documents and correspondence from her various activities. Also includes certificates from courses in organizing or other union programs, and a folder of resumes from different stages of her organizing career.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1996-2007, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - El-Amin's resumes, 1990s and undated (Box 15)
  - Oral history transcript, 1997 (Box 15)
  - Marriages and divorces, 1982-1983 (Box 15)
  - Certificates and training, 1984-2009 (Box 15)
  - Fliers for events featuring El-Amin, 2000-2005 (Box 15)
- Black Liberation Historical Documents, 1965-1967 and undated, 1 box
  Articles and pamphlets acquired by El-Amin relating to the Black Panther Party and the Black Liberation movement of the 1960s. Highlights include a transcript of Stokely Carmichael, Chairman of SNCC, speaking at the 1966 Berkeley conference on Black Power and its Challenges. Includes articles on the condition of African Americans by Bayard Rustin, as well as coverage of the Watts riot and recovery of the Watts area. Also includes several issues of Commentary Reports from the 1960s.
  - Sociology course bibliographies, 1967 (Box 15)
  - Articles on Watts and other protests, 1960s (Box 15)
  - Black Power/Black Panthers, 1960s (Box 15)
    Scope and Contents
    Stokely Carmichael speech, Berkeley Conference on Black Power & Its Challenges, 1966
  - Black Power/Black Panthers, 1960s (Box 15)
    Stokeley Carmichael "What We Want," 1966
  - News clippings re: Berkeley, 1960s (Box 15)
  - Bayard Rustin articles, 1960s (Box 15)
  - Commentary Reports, 1965 and undated (Box 15)
- Conferences, 1985-2010, 1 box
  Conference books, fliers, correspondence, and handouts from various conferences El-Amin attended. There is some overlap between this series and the Organizations and Movements series. Conferences have been arranged alphabetically.
  - All Black Male Conference, 1985 (Box 16)
  - Black Theodicy Forum, UNC, 2010 Aug. (Box 16)
  - Black Youth in the Age of Obama, 2010 (Box 16)
  - Congressional Black Caucus Fall Braintrust, 2009 (Box 16)
  - Durham Human Relations Unity Conference, 2007, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Feminism: Gender, Race, and Class workshop, 2007, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - LA Labor Left Conference, 2000 (Box 16)
  - Labor Notes Conferences, 2001 and 2003 (Box 16)
  - Labor Notes Conference: Rebuilding Labor's Power, 2008 (Box 16)
  - National NOW Conference, 2007 (Box 16)
  - National Organizers Alliance: NOA Gathering V, 2001 June-July (Box 16)
  - Organizing in Healthcare, 1993 (Box 16)
  - Southeast Social Forum, 2006 (Box 16)
  - Southern Faith, Labor, and Community Alliance, 2007 (Box 16)
  - Southern Human Rights Organizers Conference (SHROC VI), 2006 Dec. (Box 16)
  - Southern Human Rights Organizers Conference (SHROC VII), 2008 Dec. (Box 16)
  - Southern Strategies: The Economy and the Election Agenda, 2008 (Box 16)
  - Veterans of the Mississippi Civil Rights Movement, 2008 Mar. (Box 16)
  - Work Experience Program (WEP) Coalition, 1997 Nov. (Box 16)
- Photographs and Audiovisual Materials, 1970s-2012
  Photographs and videotapes from El-Amin's activities, dating from the 1970s through the 2000s. Most of the series consists of loose photographs, which El-Amin has sorted by event; there are also 4 albums with similar contents. There are photographs of several events represented in the Organizations and Movements series, including the Black Radical Congress Southern Regional Conference; SPICE graduations; union rallies and protests; political and anti-war demonstrations; meetings of groups such as Jobs with Justice, SARN, NAACP, and Black Workers for Justice; and other activist events. These have been housed by event in separate photo packets, with any accompanying information recorded on the outside of each packet. El-Amin's family photographs are much less organized, with few captions or dates included. Includes photographs of her three weddings.
  The 7 VHS tapes are largely promotional or informational media produced for BWFJ or for unions. Finally, there are 18 DVDs, which are largely related to Southern Anti-Racism Network events.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access note. Series contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
  - Loose photographs (Box 16)
    - Family, loose and unsorted, 1970s-1980s and undated, 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Immigrant Workers Freedom Ride, NC Mutual Building, Durham, 2003 Sept., 9 photos (Box 16)
    - BWFJ Ina Mae Best Campaign, RI, 1991, 14 photos (Box 16)
    - 1199 New England fight to save the Jewish Home from closing, 1992, 22 photos (Box 16)
    - Grass Roots Institute for Fundraising (GIFT), Sea Island, Ga., 2004, 26 photos (Box 16)
    - 10th Anniversary of NAFTA protest, Greensboro, 2004, 7 photos (Box 16)
    - SPICE Leadership Training, undated, 8 photos (Box 16)
    - SPICE Graduation, Weaver St. Center, undated, 27 photos (Box 16)
    - Celebrating Steve Bloom's 60th birthday with SPICE and SARN, undated, 4 photos (Box 16)
    - Khalilah's Jewelry, undated, 2 photos (Box 16)
    - Triangle JWJ and Labor Notes joint conference at UNC Friday Center, 2000, 27 photos (Box 16)
    - Nellie Hester, Joan Gibbs, and Brenda Stokely; New York Radical Women, undated, 4 photos (Box 16)
    - Families living around Durham Food Service Restaurant, before site was sold to Union Baptist Church, undated, 12 photos (Box 16)
    - International Women's Day, celebrating South African women and end of apartheid, 1991 or 1992, 10 photos (Box 16)
    - Witness for Peace Southeast Steering Committee meeting, 2007?, 3 photos (Box 16)
    - SPICE event at The Know Bookstore, 2005 or 2006, 1 photo (Box 16)
    - SARN 5th Anniversary celebration at Hayti Heritage Center and conference at Union Baptist Church, 2004 June, 32 photos (Box 16)
    - Launch of Triangle JWJ, 1998 Aug., 8 photos (Box 16)
    - Anti-war demonstration, Solidarity comrades and other radicals, undated, 18 photos (Box 16)
    - SPICE graduation, WD Hill, 2006, 26 photos (Box 16)
    - NC NAACP Labor forum in support of Smithfield workers, 2007, 18 photos (Box 16)
    - JWJ anti-sweat campaign with UNC students, at Wal-Mart, Durham, undated, 10 photos (Box 16)
    - Launch of SPICE at Snow Building (SARN Office), 2001 Aug. 16, 11 photos (Box 16)
    - Mayor Tennyson, Forum Against Gang Violence, City Hall, undated, 15 photos (Box 16)
    - Anne Wolfley, Snow Building meeting, undated, 3 photos (Box 16)
    - SPICE families attend anti-war demonstration in Washington, DC, after Katrina, 2007, 1 photo (Box 16)
    - SARN office, Snow Building, 2001, 1 photo (Box 16)
    - Education NOT Incarceration presentation, Michelle Cotton-Laws, Durham Main Library, 2000 or 2001, 19 photos (Box 16)
    - Venezuelan dignitaries visit, undated, 18 photos (Box 16)
    - Leader of failed Blue Cross campaign, Toledo, OH, 1988, 1 photo (Box 16)
    - Black-Brown Unity Conference, Highlander Center, 2007 Feb., 10 photos (Box 16)
    - Labor Notes Policy Committee meeting, Detroit, undated, 4 photos (Box 16)
    - District 1199-New England Jewish Home grievance victory, Providence, RI, 1991, 8 photos (Box 16)
    - Labor Notes and SARN/JWJ conference, Friday Center, 2000 April, 8 photos (Box 16)
    - Protest for Global Economic Justice with SPICE and Socialist Party, Washington, DC, undated, 10 photos (Box 16)
    - SARN Closing the Achievement Gap forum, Daniella Cook, undated, 15 photos (Box 16)
    - BWFJ Solidarity meeting with Ashaki Binta, undated, 12 photos (Box 16)
    - JWJ campaign to organized Duke nurses, undated, 23 photos (Box 16)
    - SPICE fundraiser at Sharon Nelson's, undated, 5 photos (Box 16)
    - Labor Notes Policy Committee meeting, undated, 11 photos (Box 16)
    - Center for Third World Organizing (CTWO) CAT training with SPICE, undated, 12 photos (Box 16)
    - Durham NAACP officers, 2004?, 4 photos (Box 16)
    - IUOE contract campaign to win community service hours from Duke, 2001, 24 photos (Box 16)
    - NAACP National Convention, Detroit, 2007, 15 photos (Box 16)
    - Gathering signatures and demonstrating against sweatshops, Wal-Mart, 1998 or 1999, 14 photos (Box 16)
    - Anti-war demonstration with Solidarity comrades, undated, 17 photos (Box 16)
    - JWJ demonstration, Rashid Muhammad and Maurice Hines, undated, 12 photos (Box 16)
    - Day Against Police Brutality, Hayti Heritage Center after march from Durham Jail, Oct. 22 [unknown year], 16 photos (Box 16)
    - Million Family March on Washington, DC, with Nation of Islam, 2000, 28 photos (Box 16)
    - Leon Davis memorial service, attended by 1199 New England staff and leaders, 1993, 1 photo (Box 16)
    - SARN Education NOT Incarceration visiting session, Durham Main Library, 2000 or 2001, 24 photos (Box 16)
    - Theresa El-Amin, Rhode Island, 1997, 1 photo (Box 16)
    - SARN founding conference, 1999 June, 1 photo (Box 16)
    - Last days with friends in Cleveland, 1990, 5 photos (Box 16)
    - Coalition of Labor Union Women, Atlanta, mid-1980s, 2 photos (Box 16)
    - Coalition of Labor Union Women 5th Anniversary celebration, 1995, 1 photo (Box 16)
    - Millions More movement, Washington, DC, 2005, 6 photos (Box 16)
    - Black Radical Congress organizing committee before June 1998 conference, Chicago, 1 photo (Box 16)
    - Conference at ERUUF on Racial Justice with Project South (Atlanta) facilitating, undated, 8 photos (Box 16)
    - People of Faith gathering in support of UFCW Smithfield campaign and Sabbath Economics, Summer 2007 or 2008, 24 photos (Box 16)
    - Justice for Mumia Rally, Philadelphia, with Solidarity comrades, undated, 21 photos (Box 16)
    - JWJ National meeting, Kentucky?, undated, 5 photos (Box 16)
    - SARN Education NOT Incarceration campaign launch, Close the Achievement Gap, 2000 Aug., 24 photos (Box 16)
    - JWJ rally at McDonald's to raise minimum wage, Providence, RI, 1995 or 1996, 3 photos (Box 16)
    - Poor Peoples March and Rally, Philadelphia, 2001?, 18 photos (Box 16)
    - SEIU Local 285-African American Caucus meeting, 1995, 13 photos (Box 16)
    - NOW Detroit meeting, 2007 July, 8 photos (Box 16)
    - Passing anti-sweatshop ordinance in Durham, 2000 Aug., 8 photos (Box 16)
    - Triangle JWJ-Union Baptist Church, Durham, 1999, 14 photos (Box 16)
    - Launch of Organize the South Midwest Tour, Cleveland, Ohio, 1989, 7 photos (Box 16)
    - Project South and Triangle JWJ at ERUUF, Durham, 2000, 9 photos (Box 16)
  - Photograph albums (Box 17)
    - Unlabeled activism album (Box 17)
    - Black Radical Congress Southern Regional Conference, undated, 3 albums (Box 17)
  - VHS tapes
    - Organize the South, BWFJ (Box 17)
    - Justice for Keysville Now! (Box 17)
    - Workers Want Fairness documentary--Rocky Mtn. Undergarment and Workers Unity Council, 1989 Nov. 9 (Box 17)
    - Toxic Terrorism--the Shiloh Coalition Fights Back (Box 17)
    - BWFJ Meeting, 1992 Mar. 7 (Box 17)
    - Ina Mae Best, CCRI, Providence, 1991 May 31 (Box 17)
    - Hamlet, NC: Our Jobs, Our Lives? (BWFJ) (Box 17)
  - DVDs
    - Jena, LA Civil Rights Movement, 2007 September 20 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0001)
    - Columbus, GA Human Rights Forum, 2011 December 08 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0002)
    - Congress of Southern African Trade Unions, 1986 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0003)
    - SARN Lifting Our Voices for Social Justice: Concert and Poetry Jam, 2011 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0004)
    - Southern Anti-Racism Network Education: Not Incarceration, 2011 May 23 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0005)
    - Troy Davis Press Conference, 2011 September 16 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0006)
    - S.A.R.N. Integration Debate, 2012 February 16 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0007)
    - S.A.R.N. Women's Forum, 2012 March 19 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0008)
    - S.A.R.N. Parent Focus Group, 2013 March 27 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0009)
    - S.A.R.N. Labor Rights, 2012 April 04 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0010)
    - S.A.R.N. "Building a Village", 2012 August 18 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0011)
    - S.A.R.N. Village Strategic, 2012 September 29 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0012)
    - S.A.R.N. Get Out the Vote, 2012 October 09 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0013)
    - S.A.R.N. Building a Village, 2012 October 20 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0014)
    - S.A.R.N. Thanksgiving, 2012 November 20 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0015)
    - Western Hemisphere Institute for Security Cooperation (WHINSEC) Board of Visitors Meeting: Disc 1 of 2, 2012 June 27 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0016)
    - S.A.R.N. "Build A Village", 2012 December 01 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0017)
    - S.A.R.N. Annual Fundraiser, 2013 April 26 (Box 23, Dvd RL00357-DVD-0018)
- Oversize materials, undated, 1 folder
  Foam boards and one poster from Jobs with Justice.
  - 6 Jobs with Justice foam boards with Durham community signatures for Nurses United for Patient Advocacy at Duke University Medical Center (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Trabajos con Justicia poster (Oversize-folder 1)
- Realia, undated, 4 boxes
  Includes 3 boxes of t-shirts and 1 box of buttons and other ephemera collected by El-Amin throughout her years of activism.
  - T-shirts (Box 18)
  - T-shirts (Box 19)
  - T-shirts (Box 20)
  - Buttons, bumper stickers, name tags, etc. (Box 21)